Now, when a client engages a freelancer,
عندما يتعامل العميل مع الموظف الحر
they may share a lot of information about their work and company with the freelancer.
ربما يشارك معه الكثير من التفاصيل عن عمله وشركته.
This information could be things like source code of a software application,
ويمكن لتلك المعلومات أن تشمل التعليمات البرمجية الأصلية لتطبيق برمجي،
their long-term or short-term business plans,
أو خطط أعماله قصيرة وطويلة الأمد،
a design of their product,
أو تصميم منتج من منتجاته،
even their passwords, their secret source of a key product.
أو حتى كلمات المرور الخاصة به، أو مصدره السري لمنتج مهم.
This information may be shared with
يمكن مشاركة هذه المعلومات من خلال
different methods through emails or verbally in meetings,
طرق مختلفة كالبريد الإلكتروني أو شفهيًا في الاجتماعات
through chats, even WhatsApp or Slack,
أو عن طريق المحادثات الإلكترونية، أو واتساب، أو Slack،
and in some cases shared Cloud drives.
وفي بعض الأحيان من خلال مشاركة مساحات التخزين السحابية Cloud drives.
In this case, it becomes really important for
من المهم في هذه الحالة
the client to protect the information and make
أن يحمي العميل معلوماته وأن يتأكد
sure that the freelancer takes utmost care to not
من أن الموظف الحر يحرص بشدة على ألا
transmit this information to a third party without the client approving it.
ينقل تلك المعلومات لأي طرف ثالث بدون موافقة العميل.
That's what a non-disclosure agreement really is.
هذا هو اتفاق السرية في حقيقته.
It's a legal document to ascertain that
فهو الوثيقة القانونية التي تنص على
the freelancer does not transfer any information obtained
ألا ينقل الموظف الحر أي معلومات يحصل عليها
from the client to any third party without
من العميل لأي طرف ثالث بغير
proper purpose and proper authorization as required.
سبب وجيه وتفويض حسب الحاجة.
On the other hand, a service agreement is more about the work that you do.
أما اتفاق الخدمة على الجانب الآخر فهو يتعلق أكثر بالعمل الذي تقوم به.
It's a legal document that lists down the terms of engagement between the two of you.
فهو الوثيقة القانونية التي تسرد شروط التعاقد بينكما.
Examples of things that one might include here are interim delivery schedules,
تتضمن أمثلة البنود التي يمكن إدراجها هنا جداول التسليم المؤقتة،
frequency of code drops,
ووتيرة استخدام التعليمات البرمجية الجديدة،
or weekly update schedules,
أو جداول التحديثات الأسبوعية،
working with companies that might work in the same domain as the client,
والعمل مع شركات أخرى لها نفس نشاط العميل،
hiring employees that work for the client,
وتوظيف موظفين للعمل لحساب العميل،
and also terminating the contract prematurely.
وأيضًا فسخ التعاقد قبل المدة المحددة.
Sometimes, if things go wrong and you are held liable,
أحيانًا تسوء الأمور ويتم تحميلك مسؤوليتها،
the contracts may allow unlimited liability,
وربما ينص العقد على مسؤولية غير محدودة
which means you may need to pay an indefinite amount to cover the losses.
مما يعني أنك من الممكن أن تكون مطالبًا بدفع مبالغ غير محددة من المال.
This is not a good idea,
وهذه فكرة سيئة،
especially when you're starting out.
خاصة في بداية عملك الحر.
It is always a good idea to limit your liability.
من الجيد دومًا أن تحدد نطاق مسؤوليتك.
A good idea to limit your liability is to limit it to
ومن الأفكار الجيدة لوضع حدود لمسؤوليتك هو تحديدها
a monetary amount of the all the service fee that you receive from the client.
بقدر المبلغ المالي لكل المدفوعات المستحقة من العميل مقابل خدماتك.
Another one is indemnification.
الطريقة الأخرى هي التعويض.
Indemnification happens when you need to
وهو ما تفعله حين يتعين عليك
compensate the client for a breach in the contract.
تعويض العميل عن الإخلال بالعقد.
Now you know the world is not fair and there's
أنت تعلم جيدًا أن العالم ليس عادلًا دومًا وأن هناك
a rare chance that you might get into a situation,
احتمالًا ضئيلًا بأن تجد نفسك في موقف
but the client wrongly put charges on you and you'll need to indemnify.
يتهمك فيه العميل ظلمًا ويطالبك بالتعويض.
This is not common and is very rare.
ليس هذا بالأمر الشائع وهو نادر الحدوث.
But if it does happen,
ولكنه إذا حدث
it could lead to significant monetary losses.
فمن الممكن أن يؤدي إلى خسائر مادية جسيمة.
To mitigate the risk of any such unexpected situations,
للتخفيف من مخاطر مثل تلك المواقف الغير متوقعة
it is a good idea to limit the extent of
من الأفضل لك أن تضع حدًا أقصى
indemnification to the sum of all the fee that the client paid you.
للتعويض يبلغ مجموع كل الأجور التي تحصلت عليها من العميل.
For example, if the client sues you for a million dollars and they
على سبيل المثال، إذا قاضاك العميل من أجل مليون دولار وهو
paid you $20,000 for everything that you did for them,
قد دفع لك 20,000 دولار نظير كل ما قدمته له من خدمات
you only owe them $20,000 in the lawsuit.
فأنت تدين له فقط بـ 20,000 في تلك القضية.
It's also important to make sure that contracts like
من المهم أيضًا أن تتأكد من أن التعاقدات مثل
non-disclosure agreements do not have unlimited validity.
اتفاقات السرية ليست لها فترة صلاحية غير محدودة.
A five-year period from the end of the contract is
فخمس سنوات من تاريخ انتهاء العقد هي
a good time frame to limit the validity, which means,
فترة جيدة لتحديد الصلاحية بها، مما يعني
you'll be obligated to the non-disclosure agreement until
أنك ملزم باتفاق السرية حتى بعد
five years after the contract has ended and not more than that.
انتهاء العقد بخمس سنوات ولكن ليس لأكثر من ذلك.
Lastly, it is important to put in a premature termination clause there.
وأخيرًا، من المهم أن تضع بندًا لفسخ العقد قبل الموعد المحدد.
You don't want to get stuck with a client if you don't like
فأنت لا تريد أن تجد نفسك عالقًا مع عميل لا تحب
the nature of work or you don't like the client's work culture.
طبيعة أو ثقافة عمله.
Having a premature termination clause with
أن يكون لديك بندًا لإنهاء العقد قبل الموعد المحدد
enough notice period is good for a healthy exit from any client relationship.
بفترة إخطار كافية قبلها هو شيء مهم لخروج آمن من أي علاقة عمل مع عميل.